Guide to the North African Jewish Manuscript Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Libya, 1868-1960; Series XIV
  - Official document of the Italian government regarding property of Sfani ben Hayun Naim and his future wife, 1923; MS.1825.1788; 4 pages (1 blank); 31 centimeters. (Box 36, Folder 6)
    Place: Tripoli. Among the signatories are several with Arabic names.
  - Government receipt, 1924; MS.1825.1789; 2 pages; 9 x 14 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 24)
  - Appeal to the Italian government involving a few people, 1925; MS.1825.1790; 2 pages; 35 centimeters. (Box 36, Folder 6)
    Place: Tripoli. The document is written in Italian and Arabic.
  - Document of the Italian Jewish community regarding business dealings between Arabs and Jews, 1925; MS.1825.1791; 1 leaf; 29 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 25)
    Place: Tripoli. The document lists the names of the Arab merchants.
  - Letter attesting to the 1929 appointment of Jusef Gean (Yosef Ji'an) to the rabbinic court, 1930; MS.1825.1792; 1 leaf; 31 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 25)
    Place: Tripoli. The letter is written in Italian and signed by the Italian governor of Tripoli.
  - Document in Italian regarding real estate, 1935; MS.1825.1793; 4 pages (1 blank); 31 centimeters. (Box 36, Folder 6)
    Place: Tripoli. The document is an official translation to Italian.
  - Report written in Italian concerning real estate of Hlafo Sasson, 1935; MS.1825.1794; 4 pages (1 blank); 31 centimeters. (Box 36, Folder 7)
    Place: Tripoli. The document is a report of the Italian court proceedings.
  - Court decision concerning real estate of Hlafo Sasson, 1935; MS.1825.1795; 1 leaf; 32 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 26)
  - Official certificate in Italian, 1943; MS.1825.1796; 1 leaf; 26 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 26)
    Place: Tripoli. The form includes information concerning an individual.
  - Document in Italian confirming the receipt of a stipend for studying, 1950; MS.1825.1797; 1 leaf; 14 x 22 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 26)
  - List of people and items they purchased, 1925; MS.1825.1798; 4 pages (1 blank); 37 centimeters. (Box 36, Folder 7)
    Place: Tripoli. Written on a form of the Italian government.
  - Certificate in Italian from the general prosecutor to Avraham Hakhmon, Circa 1920-circa 1940; MS.1825.1799; 1 leaf; 18 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 27)
  - Official document including one day's schedule of an Italian office, Circa 1940-circa 1960; MS.1825.1800; 1 leaf; 31 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 27)
    Place: Tripoli. The schedule includes an appointment with representatives of the Jewish community.
  - Pages from a manuscript discussing various halakhic issues, 1927; MS.1825.1801; 2 pages; 18 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 27)
    Place: Tripoli. The manuscript is written in Hebrew and Judeo-Arabic. One of the sections includes a date of 1927.
  - Page from a manuscript discussing various halakhic issues, 1927; MS.1825.1802; 1 leaf; 10 x 17 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 27)
  - Summary of a calendar for the years 1907-1931, 1894; MS.1825.1803; 2 pages; 28 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 28)
    Place: Tripoli. The summary included terminology used by experts to know when holidays would take place in future years.
  - Copy of five halakhic documents, 1930; MS.1825.1804; 2 pages; 31 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 28)
    Place: Tripoli. The first two documents are signed by Yitshak Maimon Gueta. The third document is signed by Yosef Yonah. The fourth document is signed by the chief rabbi's deputy and by Yosef Ji'an. The fifth document concerns a dispute between a husband and his wife. It is signed by Y.H., S.T. [Yissakhar Hakhmon, Sefaradi Tahor].
  - Letter to Khamus Falah, chief rabbi of Benghazi, regarding ritual slaughter, 1931; MS.1825.1805; 1 leaf; 32 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 28)
  - Halakhic decision regarding marriage (kidushin) and the legitimacy of witnesses, 1935; MS.1825.1806; 1 leaf; 31 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 28)
    Place: Tripoli. This document may be a page from a communal ledger.
  - Announcement by the court regarding the reading of the lamentation of the Ninth of Av and the prohibition against women going to a cemetery on the Ninth of Av, 1948; MS.1825.1807; 1 leaf; 14 x 19 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 28)
    Place: Tripoli. The document is written in Judeo-Arabic.
  - Page from a homily by a rabbi regarding halakhic issues, 1920-1930; MS.1825.1808; 2 pages; 24 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 29)
    Place: Tripoli. The document does not include a date but appears to be from around 1920-30 by the type of paper used. The document is written in Hebrew and appears to have been written by Yissakhar Hakhmon.
  - Document concerning laws of ritual slaughtering, Circa 1900-circa 1920; MS.1825.1809; 1 leaf; 31 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 29)
  - Page of references to halakhic sources, Circa 1920-circa 1940; MS.1825.1810; 1 leaf; 17 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 29)
  - Note with references to a halakhic book, Circa 1920-circa 1940; MS.1825.1811; 1 leaf; 18 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 29)
    Place: Tripoli. The document mentions the custom of reading Parashat Bereshit at the end of the month of Elul.
  - Halakhic decision concerning card playing, Circa 1930s; MS.1825.1812; 4 pages (2 blank); 28 centimeters. (Box 36, Folder 7)
  - List of various halakhic references, mainly with regard to marriage, Circa 1930s; MS.1825.1813; 2 pages; 28 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 30)
  - Letter regarding activities prohibited on the Sabbath, Circa 1940s; MS.1825.1814; 2 leaves; 13 x 20 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 30)
  - List of halakhic references, Circa 1940-circa 1960; MS.1825.1815; 4 pages; 15 centimeters (Box 28, Folder 30)
  - Homily praising synagogues and Talmudic academies and highlighting the importance of prayer and study, 1933; MS.1825.1816; 3 leaves; 23 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 31)
    Place: Tripoli. The anonymous homily was possibly written by a member of the rabbinic court of Tripoli.
  - One page containing various homilies, 1930s; MS.1825.1817; 4 columns; 31 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 32)
    Place: Tripoli. Homilies written in Hebrew about weekly Torah portion, family matters, and children. The handwriting appears to be from Tripoli.
  - Short novella with regard to a rabbinic homily on the role of sons and grandsons, Circa 1930-circa 1950; MS.1825.1818; 2 pages; 21 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 32)
    Place: Tripoli. The back of the document has various lists including the biblical verse, Ex. 16:16
  - Homily for Shavuot that was issued by the rabbinic court, 1952; MS.1825.1819; 2 leaves; 25 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 32)
    Place: Tripoli. Written in Judeo-Arabic. One page icludes announcements by the rabbinate in Libya.
  - Poem written by Frija Zuaretz and sent to Yissakhar Hakhmon in honor of the arrival of Shelomoh Illoz to the community, 1947; MS.1825.1820; 1 leaf; 34 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 33)
    Place: Tripoli. Frija Zuaretz later became a Member of the Knesset in Israel. [MS.1825.1752 is a letter from Yissakhar Hakhmon to Frija Zuaretz.]
  - Unknown lturgical poem praising Chaim Weitzman and David Ben-Gurion, 1949; MS.1825.1821; 1 leaf; 17 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 33)
    Place: Tripoli. The name of writer of the poem, Avraham, appears as an acrostic. Yissakhar Hakhmon copied it.
  - Unknown liturgical poems (piyyutim), Circa 1900-circa 1950; MS.1825.1822; 1 leaf; 31 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 33)
  - Unknown piyyutim (liturgical poems), Circa 1900-circa 1950; MS.1825.1823; 1 leaf; 31 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 33)
  - Three unknown liturgical poems (piyyutim), Circa 1900-circa 1950; MS.1825.1824; 2 pages; 27 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 33)
    Place: Tripoli. Two of the piyyutim were written by a writer named Yisrael and an additional piyyut was written by a writer named Avraham.
  - Liturgical poem for the ceremony at the end of the sabbath (Havdalah), honoring Elijah the prophet, Circa 1900-circa 1950; MS.1825.1825; 2 pages; 18 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 34)
    Place: Tripoli. The poem is written in Hebrew and the name of the author, Yisrael, appears as an acrostic. The document MS.1825.1843 contains the same piyyut.
  - Booklet with three piyutim, 1958; MS.1825.1826; 4 pages; 19 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 34)
    Place: Tripoli. One piyut is recited before the reading of the Ten Commandments in the synagogue, according to the custom of Libya. Two of the piyutim are unknown. There is also a dedication in memory of Shelomoh ben Eliyahu Boaron by his family who donated money to the synagogue. The booklet was printed in Israel.
  - Piyyut (liturgical poem) written by Yisrael, Circa 1930s; MS.1825.1827; 2 pages; 21 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 34)
  - Liturgical poem, Circa 1940s; MS.1825.1828; 1 leaf; 17 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 34)
    Place: Tripoli. The name Masud appears as an acrostic.
  - Piyyut (liturgical poem) written by Yitshak Hai, Circa 1900-circa 1950; MS.1825.1829; 4 pages (2 blank); 14 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 34)
    Place: Tripoli?. Written in rhymes in Hebrew. The last stanza has an alternate version on the next page.
  - List of rabbis honored at a memorial service on the night of Yom Kippur, Circa 1900-circa 1920; MS.1825.1830; 2 pages; 31 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 34)
    Place: Tripoli. This service was customary in Tripoli. The list includes about forty names of rabbis. Names of a few prominent rabbis seem to be missing from the list, while some other names included are unfamiliar.
  - Document of the rabbinical court declaring a day of fast, Circa 1940-circa 1942; MS.1825.1831; 4 leaves; 20 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 35)
    Place: Tripoli. The document was written during the period of the Second World War concerning deportation of Jews from Tripoli to concentration camps. The court declared a fast day, with the prayer that in the future there would be no need for fast days.
  - List of customs, Circa 1948-circa 1952; MS.1825.1832; 4 pages; 21 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 36)
    Place: Tripoli. The document was written by Refael Sued and a rabbi Khalfon. Refael Attia is also mentioned.
  - Decision of the rabbinical court regarding Torah scrolls and scribes, 1940; MS.1825.1833; 2 leaves; 23 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 36)
    Place: Tripoli. There are no judges' signatures on the document. It is not certain that the two leaves of the document belong together.
  - Letter from the community of Zliten, a town in Libya, to the court of Tripoli with regard to Torah scrolls, 1926; MS.1825.1834; 2 pages; 29 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 36)
    Place: Zliten. The letter is signed by Hayim Tayar and Hayim Salhub.
  - Certificate confirming the shipment of kosher cheese, 1930; MS.1825.1835; 2 pages; 13 x 15 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 36)
    Place: Groningen, Netherlands. According to the certificate of kashrut, the cheese was kosher year-round with the exception of one type of cheese that was not kosher for Passover. The cheese was sent from Groningen to Tripoli. (The cheese may have been intended for the Italians in Tripoli, since cheese was not typically part of the Libyan Jews' diet.)
  - Document describing synagogue customs, especially with regard to Torah scrolls, 1936; MS.1825.1836; 4 pages (1 blank); 31 centimeters. (Box 36, Folder 7)
    Place: Tripoli. Among the customs is the order of the Torah scrolls taken out of the ark or read on various occasions. The document is signed by Yissakhar Hakhmon, Hayim Yagour, Mosheh Lahmemi, Avraham Khalfon, Yitshak Seror, Yehudah Dador, Yosef Rubin, Eliyahu Lavi, Yamrush al-Jerbi, and Avraham Sarousi.
  - Prayer for the community, 1930 or 1940; MS.1825.1837; 2 pages; 21 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 37)
    Place: Tripoli. The prayer is written in Hebrew and Judeo-Arabic, since it it was recited before a community whose members did not all speak Hebrew.
  - List of the order of Torah readings, Circa 1900-circa 1950; MS.1825.1838; 5 leaves; 12 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 37)
  - Prayer to remove evil spirits, Circa 1900-circa 1950; MS.1825.1839; 1 leaf; 33 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 37)
    Place: Tripoli? Tsefat?. The document is the prayer of a man who wants to marry a widow but fears that he could be harmed by evil spirits that the deceased husband left in her.
  - Manuscript written in esoteric language, Circa 1930-circa 1940; MS.1825.1840; 2 pages; 19 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 37)
    Place: Tripoli. It is possible that the manuscript is a riddle.
  - Script of a play in four acts written for the Maccabee Association, a social club for Jewish boys and girls in Tripoli, 1923; MS.1825.1841; 45 leaves; 29 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 38)
    Place: Tripoli. The play is written mainly in Judeo-Arabic with some sections in Hebrew. It is about Joseph the Righteous. The author of the play is Rahum Arbiv. The script includes notes and stage directions, such as when to laugh or to cry. The script was written in 1923, with a performance planned for 1924.
  - Glossary written in literary Arabic, Circa 1900-circa 1950; MS.1825.1842; 24 pages; 15 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 39)
  - Document including a notable list of spices, medicinal herbs and fragrant herbs, Circa 1900-circa 1950; MS.1825.1843; 10 pages; 31 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 40)
    Place: Tripoli. The manuscript is written mostly in Judeo-Arabic. It appears to be pages from a larger manuscript. It also includes a liturgical poem for the ceremony at the end of the sabbath (Havdalah), honoring Elijah the prophet. The poem is written in Hebrew and the name of the author, Yisrael, appears as an acrostic. MS.1825.1825 contains the same piyyut.
  - Translations from Hebrew to Judeo-Arabic of words found in Leviticus, including names of animals, according to the Sharh tradition from Tripoli, Circa 1930-circa 1950; MS.1825.1844.1-.2; 2 pages; 23 centimeters. and 1 leaf; 17 x 21 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 41)
    Place: Tripoli. The appearance of the document suggests a date of circa 1940. The second sheet does not seem to be related.
  - Letter regarding jewelry, 1947; MS.1825.1845; 1 leaf; 19 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 41)
    Place: Tripoli. The letter is from [?] Maimon to Yosef Shu'ah.
  - Two reports of a journalist regarding political news in Israel, 1949; MS.1825.1846; 4 pages; 21 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 41)
    Place: Tripoli. The first report is about the appointment of Israeli ambassadors. The second report is on David Ben-Gurion's visit to the Histadrut convention in Petah Tikvah discussing agriculture and the new settlements.
  - Three letters in Judeo-Arabic containing articles sent for publication to the "Hayenu" [our life] newspaper published in Tripoli, 1951?; MS.1825.1847.1-.3; 6 pages; 18-20 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 42)
    Place: Sfax, Tunisia. The articles were written by Hayim Dabash in Sfax, Tunisia. The articles deal with events that took place in Israel in the 1940s. The name Daniel de Haim Berrebi is mentioned. Parts of the manuscripts are also in Hebrew. The manuscript mentions the Jewish population of the different continents.
  - Receipt for a contribution, 1923; MS.1825.1848; 1 leaf; 10 x 13 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 42)
  - Receipt for money received by the community of Tripoli, 1936; MS.1825.1849; 1 leaf; 14 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 42)
  - List of donated items, 1944; MS.1825.1850; 1 leaf; 19 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 43)
    Place: Tripoli. The items may have been donated to a synagogue. The stationary does not seem pertinent.
  - Printed card from Talmud Torah requesting money for poor, Circa 1900-circa 1950; MS.1825.1851; 2 pages; 10 x 14 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 43)
    Place: Tripoli. Mostly in Judeo-Arabic with heading in Hebrew.
  - Fragment, 1917; MS.1825.1852; 1 leaf; 14 x 16 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 43)
  - Portion of a document, 1923; MS.1825.1853; 1 leaf; 15 x 23 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 43)
    Place: Tripoli. Possibly regarding a store.
  - Fragment, 1924; MS.1825.1854; 1 leaf; 14 x 22 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 44)
  - Certificate of approval, 1947; MS.1825.1855; 2 pages; 10 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 44)
    Place: Tripoli. The certificate was given to Yeshuah [?]. No details are included.
  - Fragment, Circa 1900-circa 1950; MS.1825.1856; 1 leaf; 10 x 14 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 44)
  - Small voucher, Circa 1900-circa 1950; MS.1825.1857; 1 leaf; 14 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 44)
  - Short statement, Circa 1900-circa 1950; MS.1825.1858; 1 leaf; 17 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 45)
    Place: Tripoli. The statement is perhaps a draft. The document is not signed.
  - Court note, Circa 1900-circa 1950; MS.1825.1859; 1 leaf; 14 x 21 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 45)
  - Note, Circa 1900-circa 1950; MS.1825.1860; 2 pages; 16 x 23 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 45)
    Place: Tripoli. The note is written on the back of the bottom half of a form.
  - Fragment, Circa 1900-circa 1950; MS.1825.1861; 1 leaf; 6 x 11 centimeters. (Box 28, Folder 45)
  - Miscellaneous texts and fragments, Circa 1900-circa 1950; MS.1825.1862; Approximately 30 pages; various sizes. (Box 28, Folder 46)
- Algeria and Eastern Morroco, 1788-1949; Series XV
  Series XV contains documents related to Algeria and Eastern Morocco. Proximity, trade, and migration have made for close ties between the Jewish communities on either side of the border between Algeria and Morocco. Box 29 contains two prayer books for the High Holy Days written in Algeria, one from Constantine and the other from Annaba in northeastern Algeria. Box 30 contains a variety of other documents from Algeria, mainly from communities in the northwest, such as Oran, Tlemcen, Mostaganem and Algiers, and from communities in northeastern Morocco, such as Debdou, Oujda and Taourirt.
  - Mahzorim
    - Maḥzor Ḳonsṭanṭin, 1788; MS.1825.0253; 202 pages; 36 centimeters. (Box 29, Folder 1)
      Place: Constantine. A prayer book with liturgical poems (piyyutim) for the Days of Awe according to the distinctive version of the Jewish community in Constantine, Algeria. Manuscript in Hebrew written in block letters and North African script; later binding. Includes notes with instructions for the prayer leader. Signed by the scribe Farag' Bouchoucha.
    - High Holiday prayerbook written by members of the Halimi family, Circa 1800-circa 1820 (before 1825); MS.1825.1053; 278 pages; 20 centimeters. (Box 29A)
      Place: Anaba (Bonne). Prayer book (mah?zor) for Rosh ha-Shanah and Yom Kippur written by members of the Halimi family from ?Anaba (Bonne) in eastern Algeria near Constantine. Original tooled leather binding.
  - Algeria
    - Letter concerning a woman whose husband converted to Christianity, 1928; MS.1825.0042; 4 pages; 32 centimeters. (Box 36, Folder 8)
      Place: Tlemcen. The letter was sent from Yosef Meśaś to Yitsḥaḳ Morʻali in the city of Algiers and cites a decision of the rabbis of Istanbul. This letter is not included in the famous book of Yosef Meśaś, Otsar Ha-mikhtavim; however, letter no. 655 of Otsar ha-mikhtavim (volume 2, pages 40) which was sent to Yitsḥaḳ Morʻali, mentions the subject of this letter.
    - Letter with legal decisions on different subjects, 1886; MS.1825.0087; 4 columns (1 blank); 27 centimeters. (Box 30, Folder 1)
      Place: Tlemcen. Long letter with a legal ruling from Ḥayim Beliyaḥ, Tlemcen, West Algeria to Asher Ghami in the city of Tunis. The letter begins with thanks for the series of letters Asher Ghami had sent giving him good legal decisions on different subjects. Ḥayim Beliyaḥ also offered consolation to Asher Ghami after the death of his wife. In addition, Beliyaḥ also tells Asher that after reading his last letter regarding a betrothal (kidushin) and understanding more about the case, he decided to cancel the betrothal. Although the details of this betrothal are not elaborated in this document, it is a known case with complicated issues concerning levirate marriage. Adar 5646 [1886].
    - Letter to Chief Rabbi of Oran with regard to the violation of a young woman, 1876; MS.1825.0418; 1 leaf; 21 centimeters. (Box 30, Folder 1)
      Place: Tlemcen. The letter was sent to Mikhael Charlesville, Chief Rabbi of Oran, from Yosef Karsinti of the city of Tlemcen.
    - Letter to the chief rabbi of Oran from the rabbi of Mostaganem concerning a bill of divorce, Circa 1880-circa 1900; MS.1825.0422; 1 leaf; 20 centimeters. (Box 30, Folder 1)
      Place: Mostaganem. The name of the rabbi in Oran appears here as Meir Charlesville. The rabbi of Mostaganem is Yehudah ben Sidon. Mostaganem is in Northwest Algeria near the border with Morocco.
    - List of rabbis in various cities of Morocco, Circa 1900-circa 1920?; MS.1825.0424; 2 pages; 27 centimeters. (Box 30, Folder 2)
      Place: Oran. The list was written by David Kohen, rabbi of Oran.
    - Letter requesting assistance for a needy person, 1868; MS.1825.0425; 1 leaf; 21 centimeters. (Box 30, Folder 2)
      Place: Oran?. The letter was written by Makhluf Sarfati and was sent to Meir Charlesville.
    - Letter from the head of the Consistoire in Oran sent from the city of Tlemcen, 1871; MS.1825.0426; 4 pages (2 blank); 19 centimeters. (Box 30, Folder 2)
      Place: Tlemcen. The letter includes a complaint about the rabbi in Tlemcen, Hayim Blieh. Signed by Yitshak Rosh, Natan Assayag, [Eliyahu Lilati?] and Aharon Edre'i.
    - Lettter from David ha-Kohen Skali in Oran to Shelomoh Kohen Zaguri, 1939; MS.1825.0446; 1 leaf; 30 centimeters. (Box 30, Folder 3)
      Place: Oran. Rahamim ben Amara is mentioned.
    - Letter regarding the acquisition of a Torah scroll, 1939; MS.1825.0478; 1 leaf; 21 centimeters. (Box 30, Folder 3)
      Place: Bonne. Letter by Yaakov Shoshanah of Bonne to Mordekhai ha-Kohen of Debdou.
    - Letter regarding an ancient document owned by Ezer Sherki, 1949; MS.1825.0482; 6 pages; 21 centimeters. (Box 36, Folder 8)
      Place: Algiers. The letter was sent from Algiers to Yemin Ha-Kohen of Tangier. It is written in Hebrew and French.
    - Letter from the rabbis in Oran to the rabbis of Tangier with regard to appointing an emissary who will deliver a bill of divorce, 1932; MS.1825.0483; 1 leaf; 21 centimeters. (Box 30, Folder 4)
      Place: Oran.
    - Document testifying to the fact that a certain gentleman is a bachelor, 1934; MS.1825.0484; 1 leaf; 21 centimeters. (Box 30, Folder 4)
      Place: Saint- Denis-du-Sig. The testimony is by Shimon El Hayani.
    - Letter from David Kohen Skali from Oran to Shelomoh ha-Kohen regarding corresponding with each other and matters of health, 1938; MS.1825.0489; 1 leaf; 28 centimeters. (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Renewal of a ketubah, 1933; MS.1825.0536; 1 leaf; 27 centimeters. (Box 30, Folder 5)
      Place: Temouchent. Document in which Masud ha-Kohen ben Eliyahu ha-Kohen renews the ketubah of his wife Ester bat Avraham Abitbol. The document is signed by Hayim ben Harosh and Maimon ben Saadon.
    - Legal decision by Yehudah Almalih, 1724 or 1725; MS.1825.0701; 2 pages; 20 centimeters. (Box 30, Folder 5)
      Place: Algiers.
    - Letter requesting financial assistance, Circa 1790-circa 1810; MS.1825.0710; 1 page; 30 centimeters. (with some writing on other side) (Box 30, Folder 5)
      Place: Mostaganem. A letter requesting financial assistance sent by Shelomoh Sarfati of Mostaganem (northwestern Algeria) to Isaac Guetta in Trieste and to Rabbi Shemama in Tunis.
    - Letter from Yeuda de-Eliyahu (i.e., son of Eliyahu) Kohen in Mostaganem to Yaakov Shukrun, possibly in Oujda, 1895; MS.1825.0729; 2 pages; 26 centimeters. (Box 30, Folder 6)
      Place: Mostaganem. On the reverse side there are passages from the Book of Esther and blessings, perhaps a practice page for a scribe.
    - Legal document relating to real estate in Tétouan, 1918; MS.1825.0766; 4 pages (2 blank); 34 centimeters. (Box 30, Folder 6)